Guide to the Italian Castle Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- MISCELLANY, 23 documents, 12 in manuscript, 11 in print.
  - Metastasio, Pietro. Fileno a Nice, and Nice in risposta...2 poems. Printed. 1 double page. Double folio broadside. (Box 33, Folder 23)
- DIPLOMATIC REPORTS AND INSTRUCTIONS, 9 manuscript documents in Italian. 627 pages and
  2 page ms. index, numbered ff. 1-280. Folio. Contemporary limp vellum. Rome, 1607- post 1663.
  - Sagredo, Nicolo. Relatione Della Corte di Francia Del Caualier Nicolo Sagredo Della Repub. Veneta. Ms. 135 pages. (Rome, n.d.). (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Minutoli, Antonio. Relatione della Corte di Spagna di Antonio M. Ambassador al Rè Filippo Quarto Per la Republ. di Lucca l'anno 1662. Ms. 222 pages. (Rome), 1662. (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Altouiti, Giacomo. Instruttione Lasciata Da Monsig. Giacomo Altouiti Arciuescovo D'Atene... Ms. 156 pages. (Rome, after 1663). (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Verospi, Monsignor. Instruttione a Monsig. Verospi Auditore di Rota... Ms. 28 pages. Rome, January 13, 1622. (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Lancellotti, Monsig. Instruttione a...Monsig. Lancellotti Vesc. di... Ms. 39 pages. Rome, Dec. 10, 1622. (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Verospi, Monsig. Ordine à...Monsignor Verospi... Ms. 9 pages. Rome, January 13, 1622. (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Allaccio, Dott. Instruttione à Dottor Allaccio, Scrittore della Biblioteca Vaticana andare in Germani... Ms. 10 pages. Rome, October 23, 1622. (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Vescouo d'Anglone. Instruttione à...Monsig. Vescouo d'Anglone Dessinato da...Suo Nuntio in Toscana. Ms. 14 pages. Rome, August 20, 1622. (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Vescouo Di Rimini. Instruttione à...destinato Nuntio alla Republica di Venetia dalla...Papa Paolo V. Ms. 14 pages. Rome, June 4, 1607. (Box 34, Folder 9)
- POLITICAL AND ECCLESIASTICAL HISTORIES, 15 documents in manuscript, mostly in Latin, some in
  Italian. 606 pages, numbered ff. 1-313. 4to. Contemporary limp vellum. Naples (and other places), 1643 and undated, around the middle of the 17th century.
  - Benedetto de Bienna. (A Neapolitan notary). Copy of Agreements signed by the Noblemen of the Sedile of Nilo in 1507. Ms. in Italian. 18 pages, numbered ff. 1-10. (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Vincenzo Orazio Scipione and Giordano Galuzzi. Excerpts from the trial, dated Feb. 28, 1576. Ms. in Latin. 6 pages, numbered ff. 13-15. Naples, May 28, 1643. (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Guarino d'Aversa, Silvestro. Diarii. Ms. in Italian. 95 pages, numbered ff. 17-56. These journals contain notations about appointments, salary paid to various officials; mention of the most important events occurring in Naples from 1434 to 1553. (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Crasullo, Angelo. Taranti ex Notario Angelo Crasullo. Ms. in Latin. 15 pages, numbered ff. 57-64. Historical notes covering the period from 1352 to 1415; in addition, an excerpt from an old parchment codex relating to events that took place in 1359 and 1362. N.p., n.d. (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Amalfi. Cronica Amalphitana. Ms. in Latin. 24 pages, numbered ff. 65-76. (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Amalfi, archbishops of. Cronica Archieporum omnium Amalfitanoru... Ms. in Latin. 30 pages, numbered ff. 77-91. A Chronicle concerning all the archbishops of Amalfi, from the year 339 onwards. (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Sicily. Compilatio Chronicarum Regni Sicilie... Ms. in Latin. 38 pages, numbered ff. 93-111. A chronicle relating to Sicilian history. (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Romualdo. Annali di cose notabili from the Chronica Romualdi. Romualdo was Archbishop of Salerno who wrote a chronicle embracing the period from the beginning of the world to the year 1125; the whole Chronica was printed by L. Muratori in Rerum Italicarum Scriptores. Ms. in Italian. 110 pages, numbered ff. 113-167. (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Cronica... Ms. in Italian. 46 pages, numbered ff. 168-194. Excerpts from different Chronicles; among them, one from the Chronicle of the Monastery of Cava (ff. 168 ff.) and from archival material. (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Tabula. Transcript from the rolls of the Chancery of Charles I, Charles II, and Robert of Anjou. Ms. in Latin. 30 pages, numbered ff. 198-213. Important material for the political, social, economic, administrative history of Naples. The Rolls (Registri) of the Chancery cover the period 1269- c. 1344. (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Naples. Registri Regis...Ms. in Latin. 42 pages, numbered ff. 214-234. Excerpts from the Neapolitan Chancery, covering the reigns of Charles I, Charles II, Charles III, Robert, Queen Johanna, King Ladislas. (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Medici. Ms. 2 pages, numbered ff. 235-236. List of Neapolitan physicians. (Box 35, Folder 12)
  - Notarii. Ms. 3 pages, numbered ff. 237-238. List of Neapolitan notaries. (Box 35, Folder 13)
  - Naples. Vetusta Napolis monumenta ex Archivo Magnae Regiae Curiae... collecta ab anno 1239 ad 1423. Ms. 96 pages, numbered ff. 240-287. In Latin. Information and lists of most ancient monumnets, notable things, collected in Naples, covering 1239-1423, collected by the Magna Regia Curia Sicula. (Box 35, Folder 14)
  - Aquino, D'. Discorso della Famiglia d'Aquino. Ms. in Italian. 51 pages, numbered ff. 288-313. (Box 35, Folder 15)
- LE 6 MONARCHIE DEL MONDO...
  - c. 386 pages, numbered ff. 1-193. Manuscript in Italian, in two columns, with many one-column insertions referring to the respective material. N.pl., n.d., apparently written in the 18th century. (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Le 6 Monarchie del Mondo. A large volume of compiled information concerning world history. No sources are given. The volume includes an index of 4 pages at the beginning.
- DOCUMENTS FROM THE WAR OF THE SPANISH SUCCESSION, 93 documents, 28 of them printed and 65 in
  manuscript, comprising c. 519 pages. Small folio. Contemporary vellum. Italy, beginning of the 18th century.
  - (Naples). Protesta stipulata per mano di pubblico Notaro in questa città di Napoli Segretamente per essentarsi dalle violenze il giorno ultimo d'Aprile 1702. Printed broadside, being a protest by the aristocracy and citizenry of Naples against the Duke of Anjou (Philip V of Spain) and Spanish rule, in favor of the Emperor. 1 page, 4to. (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Universis, & singulis Potestatibus, Capitaneis, Vicariis Iurisdicentibus Serenissimae Republicae Venetae. A printed broadside, in Italian, printed in Treviso and dated Jan. 7, 1702. It is a proclamation in the name of Vincenzo Coronelli, the Venetian cosmographer, who had been elected General of the Franciscan Conventuals in 1701, concerning the Order; signed by three provincials. Apparently extremely rare, not listed in Armao's Coronelli bibliography. (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Anne, Queen of England. Copy of a letter in Latin to the King of Spain, dated March 20, 1702, the first day of her reign, after succeeding William III who died March 19, 1702. 1-1/2 pages. (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Napoli 17.Aple 1702. Report of a naval victory in April, 1702. 2-1/2 pages. (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Nota della cariche, Corte e Famiglia della legatione di Napoli. A list of the members of the legation, headed by Cardinal Carlo Barberino, sent by Pope Clement XI to King Philip V in Naples in May 1702. Also includes presents offered to the king (see Pastor XV, pp. 22-23). 4 pages ms. (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - (Lamberg, Count Leopold Joseph von, German Ambassador in Rome). Copy of a report, apparently a diary entry, dated March 20, 1702, on the fight between Cardinal Toussaint de Forbin-Janson, Ambassador of Louis XIV in Rome and a Neapolitan gentleman, Marchese Cesare del Vasto. (See Pastor XV, p. 21). 3 pages ms. (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Grimani, Cardinal Vincenzo and Cardinal Fabrizio Paolucci. Copy of a correspondence between the Cardinal Grimani, who complains in the name of the Emperor Leopold I, to Cardinal Paolucci about the legation to the Duke of Anjou (Philip V) in Naples (see no. 5 above). With Paolucci's answer. Both letters are dated May 7, 1702. Also a third, unsigned, letter of May 8 referring to the same matter of the legation. 3 pages ms. (See Pastor XV, pp. 22-23). (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Lettere diverse sopra la success(io)ne di Filippo V alla Monarchia delle Spagne e sue dipendenze in risposta al Favoloso Leone. This defense against a book hostile to Philip V consists of an introduction concerning the falsehoods in the book and five letters on the subject of the Spanish Succession. Undated and unsigned (1703). 31 pages. (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - (Sarto, Andrea del). Two documents relating to the purchase of the altar painting "Madonna and child with St. Francis," originally in the Convent of St. Francis in Florence, by Archduke Ferdinand II of Medici. A copy from the Book of Records with an original certificate from the Bishopric of Florence, dated May 7, 1703, with the original seal and stamp. 4 pages. (The painting is today in the Pitti Palace in Florence). (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - Doni portati alla Santa Casa dalli 3 Febraro 1703 sino alli 9 Marzo da alcune citta, Terre Castelli, Congregazione...che sono venute a venerare il Santuario, a ringraziare al bellisima Virgine per haverle libertate da tutti li mali, e pericoli del Terremoto. A list of gifts (money, silver chalices, etc.) offered to the Virgin after the earthquake of February 1703. 2-1/2 pages. (Box 37, Folder 10)
  - Alla S(anti)ta Nostro Sig(no)re Clemente XI, Die 19.Februarii 1703...Per li Conservatori del Popolo Romano. A petition to Pope Clement XI urging special Church ceremonies as a thanksgiving after the earthquake of February 1703. Among others, it is suggested that all carnival festivities and masquerades be suspended for 5 years. Title and four pages. (Box 37, Folder 11)
  - Stato dell'Anime della Città di Roma. A census of the Roman population from 1703 to 1712, specified into various classes, including parishes, houses, and families, clergy, scholars, poor in hospitals, prisoners, births, deaths, etc. The total averages between 132,000 and 134,000. 2 pages. (Box 37, Folder 12)
  - Distinta relatione delle rendite e pesi della menza Vescovale di Recanati... A detailed list of the revenues of the Bishop of Recanati, 1720. 3 pages. (Box 37, Folder 13)
  - A Maggior Gloria di Deo e Merito Dell'Anime Elemosiniere. A printed leaflet, a kind of fundraising letter for the poor. It is interesting in connection with Pope Clement XI's work for church reform and his interest in inner missions. 3 pages. Rome, Gio. Giacomo Komarek Boemo, 1703. 4to. (Box 37, Folder 14)
  - Paolucci, Cardinal Fabrizio. Copy of a letter concerning incidents between the Venice merchant fleet and French vessels, as reported to him by the Nuncio in Venice. Dated Rome, April 11, 1703. (Box 37, Folder 15)
  - (Paolucci, Cardinal Fabrizio). Copy of a letter to Cardinal Paolucci by the nuncio in Venice concerning French vessels and the Venetian merchant fleet. Dated Venice, March 31, 1703. Also Paolucci's answer to him, dated April 15, 1703. 4 pages. (Box 37, Folder 16)
  - Cosimo III de'Medici, Grand Duke of Toscana. Original letter to Cardinal Carpegna, written by a secretary and signed "Il Principe di Toscana." Dated Florence, March 18, 1703. Concerning the commutation of a sentence of Ghirlandi, a nobleman. 1 page, folio, folded. (Box 37, Folder 17)
  - (Cosimo III de'Medici, Grand Duke of Toscana). Original letter from Lancellotti to the Grand Duke of Toscana (?) apparently to be submited by the Cardinal Carpegna. Written by a secretary and signed Lancellotti. Concerning the arrival of his son, Cavaliere dal Pozzo, into Florence and his marriage. Dated Rome, Feb. 28, 1703. 2 pages. (Box 37, Folder 17a)
  - Cortigiani, Michel Carlo, Bishop of Pistoia. Alli sue Diletti Cooperatori nella saluta dell'Anime. Printed leaflet, exhorting the ministers of his diocese to apply themselves with more zeal to the study of spiritual books and to their flocks. Dated Pistoia, May 31, 1704. 2 leaves. Pistoia, nella stamperia Episc. di Stefano Gatti. (Box 37, Folder 18)
  - Negroni, Cardinal Gian Francesco. Copy of a letter, in Italian and Latin, to Cardinal Francesco Maria de'Medici in Florence. Dated August 1, 1704. 1 page. (Box 37, Folder 19)
  - Viaggi che si faranno con la Sacra Imagine della Beata Virgine di San Luca nelli trè giorni delle Rogazioni. Printed pamphlet, with a woodcut of the Virgin of St. Luke and armorial woodcuts, describing the procession of the Miraculous Image of the Virgin of St. Luke of Bologna during the Rogation Days, from Sunday, April 27-Wednesday, April 30, 1704. 2 leaves, each page framed by a double rule. Bologna, nell'Impressoria Archivescovale. (Box 37, Folder 20)
  - The Column of Antonius). Notie che da me si sottoscrivono circa l'operato e quella doverà operarsi nel calare la Colonna Antonina. Remains of the ancient Roman column of Antoninus had been excavated in 1703 and Clement XI intended to have it erected in front of the Court of Justice. The technical problem proved quite difficult and was finally solved by Francesco Fontana in 1705. The anonymous writer of the present document finds fault with the work by Francesco's father Carlo Fontana and refers to Domenico Fontana's feat of moving the obelisk in the 16th century. (See Pastor XV, pages 370-371.) Dated, Nov. 25, 1704. 4 pages. (Box 37, Folder 21)
  - Philippus Baro de Mantico. Apparently the transcription of an epitaph to his wife, dated 1704. In Latin. 1 page. (Box 37, Folder 22)
  - Ponderatione seconda del Soldato Dalla Mirandola...di Carlo Terzo vero Monarca delle Spagne. Printed pamphlet on the question of the Spanish Succession. The present pamphlet is allegedly translated from a French version. Title page and 46 pages (apparently not complete). Mirandola, March 16, 1704. Small 4to. (Box 37, Folder 23)
  - Augustus II, King of Poland. Declaratio respectu Costodiae Rever. Episcopi Posnanienses. Printed proclamation to the Bishops of Posen. Dated Sept. 16, 1704. 3 pages. Apparently very rare, not in the catalogues of the BM or the BN. (Box 37, Folder 24)
  - Katzenelnbogen, Johann Anton Knebel von, Bishop of Eichstatt. Al Sagro Collegio. Two printed letters to the Sacred College. Both are addressed by hand to the Cardinal Carpegna. 4 leaves. Rome, nella stamperia della Rev.Cam.Apost., 1705. (Stained). (Box 37, Folder 25)
  - Alstalli, Cardinal Fulvio. Sincerissimo, ma altrettanto detestablie fatto, sotta Parole di Fede, successa all truppe Alemane in Figarolo. Printed proclamation by Cardinal Astalli, papal nuncio in Ferrara, concerning the German troops in Ficcarolo at the Po, in the territory of the Church. The Germans eventually left Ficcarolo on June 24. Dated Ferrara, June 20, 1704. 2 leaves. (See Pastor XV, p. 25.) (Box 37, Folder 26)
  - (Clement XI, Pope). Notificazione. Printed announcement, stating that beginning with the new year, the Pope will hold one public audience on the first Monday of each month, the first being Jan. 5, 1705. Broadside, oblong small folio, folded. Rome, nella stamperia della Rev. Cam. Apost., 1705. (Box 37, Folder 27)
  - (Gigli, Girolamo). Copia di Lettera dell'Imperatore della Cina à Papa Clemente XI. Copy of a satirical letter, ridiculing the Chinese missions of the Jesuits. Undated, unsigned. (c. 1706). 3 pages. Also 1 page: Regalo mandato dall'Imperatore della Cina al Papa. A list of presents sent by the Pope to the Emperor of China, probably part of Gigli's letter. Together 4 pages. (Box 37, Folder 28)
  - Gerbillon, Jean Francois, S.J. Decretum Ex originali Tartarico versum. Imperial decree, translated into Latin from the Tartar language by Gerbillon, General of the Jesuit mission in Peking. 1-1/2 pages. Undated (1706). (Box 37, Folder 29)
  - Thomas, Antoine, S.J. Epistola ad superiores singulorum Ordinum Qui sunt in Sina. Letter in Latin, written to the heads of various Orders doing missionary work in China. Signed by Antoine Thomas, substituting for J.F. Gerbillon, the Jesuit General, who was then ill. Dated Peking, Dec. 28, 1706. 2 pages. (Box 37, Folder 30)
  - Thomas, Antoine, S.J. Another copy of the above letter (#30), with some variants. 3 pages. (Box 37, Folder 31)
  - (Raimondo Cavaliere de Lauda). Printed broadside, being the obituary in Latin of a Dominican Friar Raimondi Cavaliere de Lauda (Lodi?) who died in his 66th year. Dated Rome, Convent of S. Sabina, March 30, 1706. (Box 37, Folder 32)
  - Ex Congregatione Consitoriali 27 Januarii 1707. -Conclusione del Voto. Notes on the Consistory of Jan. 27, 1707, listing the attending Cardinals and giving the result of the vote concerning election matters. 3 pages, 8vo. (Box 37, Folder 33)
  - Zmajevich, Vincent, Bishop of Antivari. Copy of a letter concerning a marriage between a Turkish woman and a Catholic man. Dated Perasto, June 29, 1707. 2 pages. (Box 37, Folder 34)
  - Clement XI, Pope. Breve...ad Archepiscopum Ebredunensem. Printed breve of Pope Clement XI to Charles Brulart de Genlis, Archbishop of Embrun concerning his position in regards to Nizza and Savoy. (See Pastor XV, p. 250, who does not mention this Breve). Dated August 27, 1707. Montefiascone, Typis seminaris, 1707. 6 pages. This is one of the earliest imprints of Montefiascone. (See Fumagalli, Lex.Typog.Ital, p. 244, who does not include this Breve.) (Box 37, Folder 35)
  - Indice delle Lezzioni et Anatomiche Dimostrazione...sotto la Direzione del Signor Mario Cecchini. Broadside of announcement of medical lectures and anatomical demonstrations in the Hospital del Santissimo Salvatore ad Sanct Sanctorum in Rome, under the direction of Mario Cecchini, head surgeon and anatomist of the Hospital. 19 courses by various medical and anatomical lecturers are announced from March 10 to April 18, 1707. Oblong folio, folded. Rome, nella Stamperia di Dom. Ant. Ercole in Parione. There is a contemporary ms. note that the introductory lecture had to be postponed from March 10 to March 17. (Box 37, Folder 36)
  - Note del Regalo che ha fatto presentare nella venuta in Massa il Signor Principre Eugenio Gio. Francesco di Sueson (Soissons?) alla...Principessa sua Futura Sposa...Maria Teresa Cybo... A list of diamonds and other jewelry and finery given to his fiancée. Undated. 3 pages. (Box 37, Folder 37)
  - Paolucci, Cardinal Fabrizzio. Copia di lettera...scritta alla Cardinale Gualterio sotto il primo Giugno 1707. Copy of a letter from Cardinal Paolucci to Cardinal Francesco Antonio Gualtieri, Nuncio to France who had been made Cardinal by Clement XI in 1706. 1 page. (Box 37, Folder 38)
  - Lettera scritta dal arescial. di Tessé alla Sta. di N.S. Clemente XI li 18.Decembre 1708. Copy of a letter by Marshal Tessé to Pope Clement XI. 2-1/2 pages. (Box 37, Folder 39)
  - Grimani, Cardinal Vincenzo. Copia di viglietto scritta...alle...Cardinale Paolucci Segretario di Stato di N.S. li 31 Gennaro 1707. Copy of a letter to the Secretary of State, Cardinal Paolucci; also of a letter by him of the same date to José Molines, auditor of the Rota. 2 pages. (Box 37, Folder 40)
  - (Daun, Wirich Philipp Lorenz, Count). Lettera d'un Gentiluomo d'Ascoli ad un Ministro di Napoli. Printed pamphlet, a contemporary account of the capture of Naples by the Austrian Field Marshal Count Daun. Contains the treaty of the capitulation, dated Sept. 12, 1707, signed by the Duke d'Atri, the Count Wallis, Stefano Bellett, and the Count Daun. 27 pages. N.p., n.d. 8vo. (Box 37, Folder 41)
  - Confraternitas SS. V. Vulnerum Christi. Reverendissimi, & Celissimi...Confratres. Printed letters by the Directors of the Confraternity to its members, dated Constance, Feb. 18, 19, and 20, 1708, giving news of the members and containing obituaries of members who died between 1707 and 1708. N.p., n.d. 4 leaves. (Box 37, Folder 42)
  - (Lists of exchange rates of scudis, baiocchis, etc). 6-1/2 pages. (Box 37, Folder 43)
  - (Sacred College of Cardinals). Serenissimo Principi Josepho Roman. Regi Imperatore... Copy of a letter by the Roman Cardinals in answer to Emperor Joseph I's manifest of June 26, 1708, protesting against the Emperor's anti-papal attitude. Dated Rome, August 12, 1708. (See Pastor XV, pp. 41-42.). 5 pages. (Box 37, Folder 44)
  - (Clement XI, Pope ?). Alla Santità di N.S. Per li Marchese e Conti non intesi dalla congregatione Depurata sopra li pesi Camerali. Copy of a letter written by the aristocracy to the Pope. Undated, unsigned. 2 pages, 8vo. (Box 37, Folder 45)
  - Ad Archiepiscopum Camerucensem. Copy of a letter in Latin. 1 page, 8vo. Undated, unsigned. (Box 37, Folder 45a)
  - Carpegna, Cardinal Gaspare, Prefect of Rome. Lettera Circolare Alli Monsignori Patriarchi, Arcivescovi, Vescovi, & altri Ordinarii dell'Italia.. Printed circulatory letter to the clergy, signed by the Vicar General, decreeing reforms for the expenditures of Monks. Interesting document in connection with the endeavors for Church reform by Pope Clement XI. Dated Rome, July 28, 1708. 2 leaves. Rome, stamperia della Rev. Cam. Apost., 1708. (Box 37, Folder 46)
  - Barigioni, Filippo. Discorso sopra la fabrica del Palazzo Priorale dell'inclita Città di Velletri. Colla relazione del Sig. Filippo Barigioni Architetto. Printed pamphlet, with armorial woodcut. Treatise on the rebuilding of the Palazzo Priorale in Velletri by the Roman Architect Filippo Barigioni (1690-1753). His work in Velletri seems to be unknown (see Thieme Becker). Barigione was assigned to the palace in Velletri on Feb. 22, 1708. 4 leaves. N.p., n.d. (Box 37, Folder 47)
  - (Leopold I, Emperor). Lettera con Osservazioni Sopra d'un Libro stampato nell'Anno 1706 in Rotterdam con Titolo "Ultimi Consigli, ò sia Testamento Politico d'un Ministro dell'Imperatore Leopoldo Primo." Printed pamphlet. In answer to Leopold I's political testament. 8 leaves (the last blank). Small 4to. Lucca, July 12, 1708. (Box 37, Folder 48)
  - (Maigrot, Charles, Apostolic Vicar of Fukien). Estratto d'una lettera della Rocella delli 8. Luglio 1708. Extract in Italian from the original French, concerning the controversy over the Chinese mission. 3 pages. (Box 37, Folder 49)
  - Copia di viglietto dato del Mons. de Zuenitz(?)... Copy of a letter to a Cardinal of Clement XI, in favor of Charles III as King of Spain. Unsigned, undated. (1708). 1 page. (Box 37, Folder 50)
  - Grimani, Cardinal Vincenzo, Viceroy of Naples. Copy of a letter to a Cardinal of Clement XI, concerning Charles III, King of Spain. Grimani fell into disfavor with Pope Clement XI for his recognition of Charles III. 3 pages. (Box 37, Folder 51)
  - Grimani, Cardinal Vincenzo, Viceroy of Naples. Copia di lettera...alli Signore Cardinali Carpegna, Marescotti e Panfilio. -Copia di lettera...alla Santita...Papa Clemente XI. Copies of 2 letters by Cardinal Grimani: one dated Sept. 22, 1708, the other dated Sept. 20, 1708, both concerning Charles III. 11 pages. (Box 37, Folder 52)
  - Carpegna, Cardinal Gaspare. Copia di lettera...al Cardinale Grimani. Copy of a letter from Cardinal Carpegna to Cardinal Grimani, dated Rome, July 22, 1708. (Box 37, Folder 52a)
  - (Grimani, Cardinal Vincenzo). Copy of a letter from Rome to Grimani in answer to his letter of Sept. 22 (see #52 above) and Grimani's reply. The first letter is dated Rome, Nov. 13, 1708, Grimani's answer is dated Naples (?), Nov. 1708. 3 pages. (Box 37, Folder 53)
  - Alla somma Veneratione... Copy of a letter, dated Naples, August 4, 1708, concerning Comacchio, which had fallen into the hands of the Emperor's troops in May, 1708. 6 pages. (Box 37, Folder 53a)
  - Cardinal of Saxony. Letter in Latin to the Bishops, Cardinals, etc. Dated Vienna, Sept. 3, 1708. 2 pages. (Box 37, Folder 53b)
  - Carpegna, Cardinal Gaspare (?). Copy of a letter, dated Vatican, Dec. 20, 1708. 2 pages. (Box 37, Folder 53c)
  - Clement XI, Pope. Copy of a letter in Latin to the Deacon of St. Eustachius. Dated Rome, Sept. 1, 1708. 8 pages. (Box 37, Folder 53)